Speaker: Judi Dench is one of a golden generation of actors
who have had long and successful careers,
including Maggie Smith
Vanessa Redgrave
Ian McKellen
Michael Caine
and Anthony Hopkins.
She has acted in the theater, on TV, and in movies in a career of nearly 60 years.
Judith Olivia Dench was born on December 9th, 1934,
near York in the northern part of England.
Dench’s father was a doctor, but she had connections
from a very early age to the Theatre Royal in York
– her father was the theater’s doctor and her mother made costumes for the theater.
As a teenager, Judi Dench acted in the York Mystery Plays.
These religious plays have been performed in York
every four years since the fourteenth century.
In the late 1950s and 1960s, she acted with several important theater companies,
the Old Vic, the Royal Court, and the Royal Shakespeare Company.
In the 1970s and 1980s, Dench continued to work in the theater and on TV.
In 1978, she acted in Shakespeare’s Macbeth
with the actor Ian McKellen, both in the theater and on film.
Many people think it was one of the best performances of the play ever.
She also appeared in movies like A Room with a View in 1985 and Henry V in 1989.
In the 1990s, her career changed with two movies.
The first of these was the James Bond movie GoldenEye,
where Dench played Bond’s boss, M, usually a part for a man.
Dench was a great success in the part.
She was hard, and at the same time funny.
She played the part in eight movies,
with both Pierce Brosnan and Daniel Craig as James Bond.
The second movie that changed her career was Mrs. Brown in 1997.
This small movie was a great success, and she was nominated for an Oscar for Best Actress.
In 1998, she played Queen Elizabeth I in the comedy Shakespeare in Love.
The movie was another hit.
It won the 1999 Oscar for Best Film,
and Judi Dench won the Oscar for Best Supporting Actress.
She’s only in the movie for eight minutes, but, as usual, she was fantastic.